And they could come to our home and help us if they wanted to.
So they came with their men to help.
My father passed away 24 years ago, almost 25 years ago.
I miss him very much.
While children in other families often went hungry,
He let me and my sisters never starve.
In secret he brought eggs into town -
At that time you could not do any kind of business.
If you were coming up, you ended up in real trouble, and became publicly shameful and spoiled.
But my father secretly took our family's eggs into the city,
and switched them to cornmeal.
It was a very simple house.
The worst kind of house.
When I got married into this family, life was still not very good.
But I changed their lives.
I started raising a pig.
Then I sold the pig and used the money to buy a small donkey.
When we had bought the little donkey,
we could use it to transport detergents.
We went around to other villages,
For example, villages up in the mountains,
And replace washing powder with potatoes.
It must have been in 1997 or 1998.
It was the same year that Hong Kong was transferred to China!
I remember we had a small TV in our house when it was built.
We took the TV with us to my husband's brother's house,
And together we all watched the news on this TV.
When we built the house, we got compliments from everyone.
The house was built entirely in wood.
But after a while, everyone else started building brick houses.
So we started to think that we also wanted to build such a house.
But it would be a shame to tear down the wooden house.
It was only a few years old then.
When we built it we said it was a house we could get old in.
That our children could live there until they became old.
Everyone in the village said it.
It would have been a shame to tear it down.
So we decided to change some of our arable land to a piece of land where we could build this new house.
We started preparing to move here and build a house here instead.
We built the house in 2010.
If you compare my life as a 12-year-old and my children's lives as 12-year-olds,
you can find both similarities and differences.
One difference is that they both went to school.
Every child would then go to school.
So when my children grew up, everyone went to school.
When I was growing up, each family had only a small house.
If it was a family with many sons, but they were not married yet,
Sleep everyone on the big kang together.
In winter it was heated with dried leaves and straw.
When it was heated, everyone slept there together.
It was the same throughout northwestern China.
When we cooked, we did not use electricity.
We burned straw for cooking.
We had a stove of earth,
A large wok and a bellows.
We used the bellows to keep the fire alive.
One person stood with the bellows while another cooked the food.
When we ate we did not have a kitchen table.
Just a small table that we put on the kang.
The elderly sat on the kang and ate.
The really small kids also sat on the kang.
The older children just took their bowls and sat anywhere.
As long as they got food it was good.
When we were young,
I never left the village, I've always lived here.
When I was 40 years old or almost 40 years old ...
When I was 38 ... I forgot!
It was about then that the water was contaminated and we could no longer drink it.
If we drank our spring water, it was bad for health.
The government built water pipes so that we all had running water instead.
This water came from the mountains.
Then we all had running water at home to drink.
We didn't have to go to pick up water anymore.
At home we only used running water, it was really comfortable.
At that time, we did not have all these ideas about not having enough.
Not having enough money, or not having enough of this or that.
We didn't think so.
If you had enough to eat in the morning, but not in the evening -
Then you ate happily in the morning.
It was a common situation for families here.
But people were still happy, very happy.
Every day it was laughter and smiles.
Both among adults and children.
So how do you think it's today?
Nowadays I think ...
People who are forward -looking, they make money quickly.
But whether you make a lot of money or if you are fighting, people are still the same ...
The atmosphere is no longer filled with joy.
It's really unusual.
Now it's just about money every day.
Money, money, money.